== 字幕制作：曾淑、李丹、段金硕、张靖栩、蔡兴毛 ==
一九四五年十二月二十五日
December 25, 1945
友子 太阳已经完全没入了面
Tomoko, the sun has already sunk into the sea.
我真的已经完全看不见台湾岛了
I can't see Taiwan Island at all.
你还站在那里等我吗
fnTimes New Roman} Are you still standing there waiting for me?
【 海 角 七 号 】
Cape NO.7
我操你...
an} F**k you...
我操你妈的台北!
es New Roman} I f**k you, Taipei!
哇 这不能过喔!
New Roman} Wow, the car can't pass through!
可以啦 刚刚好!
New Roman} Yes, it can. Just enough.
可以啦 可以过啦!
mes New Roman} Yes, it can.
不行啦 太低了啦
es New Roman} No, it's too low.
可以...真的可以...
imes New Roman}Yes...it can, really...
试试看嘛 真的可以!
nTimes New Roman} Have a try. It really can.
什么试试看?
Roman} Try what?
卡住就卡住了 还试试看
s20\fnTimes New Roman} The car will get stuck. Try your ass.
你要不要上来?
New Roman} Are you getting on or not?
友子 好了没?
w Roman} Tomoko, come on.
再等一下...
Roman} Wait a minute...
要拍了 没时间了
es New Roman} Come on! We don't have all day here.
友子 走开!
oman} Tomoko, get out of the way!
好了...对不起...
s New Roman} OK...sorry...
再退后一点...
ew Roman} Back off please...
光线很好 大家再靠紧一点
Got good light. Keep it close together.
非常好!
} Excellent! Good!
靠近一点 谢谢!
New Roman} Keep it close. Thank you!
走那边...
an} Walk that way...
很好 靠近一点 靠...
nTimes New Roman} All right, come on. Keep it close now...
嘿 你以为你在干嘛?
nTimes New Roman} Hey! What do you think you're doing?
搞什么?
} Come on!
友子 我们在拍照你在干嘛?
Tomoko, we're trying to shoot here. What do you think you're doing?
好了 各位不管了
es New Roman} All right, ladies. Never mind.
专业一点 我想看到每个人笑容
Let's do it professionally, all right? I want everybody in and smile.
...非常好!
man} ...Good!
茂伯!
Uncle Mao!
茂伯...
Uncle Mao...
挂号
Registered mail!
拜托一下啦!
Roman} Come on!
年轻人好脚好手没工作很悲哀呢!
It's really pathetic for a healthy young man having no work!
不是啦主席 你不要逼我嘛!
Don't push me, Mr. Representative, please.
就真的没有缺啊!
es New Roman} There's no vacancy, really!
怎么会没缺
Roman} How could it be?
像茂伯 要八十岁了还不退
Like Uncle Mao, he's 80 but still doesn’t retire yet.
跟他招手没看到 叫他也没到
He neither sees me waving hands nor hears me greeting him.
像那种人去送信不会有危险?
Isn't it dangerous for him to deliver mails?
嘿...
Hey...
你们不行去游泳!
es New Roman} You can't go swimming!
你们明天跟等会儿都还有工作
You have work tomorrow and later on.
如果不小心晒黒了...该怎么办?
What if you get a sunburn?
只不过是玩玩水嘛!
Times New Roman} Just dabbling!
整天大呼小叫的干什么?
s20\fnTimes New Roman} What are you hollering at?
别像个老太婆一样
imes New Roman} Don't be like a crone.
嘿 专心看路 不要只看女孩!
Hey, what're you doing? Stop looking at the girls. Watch the road!
我也是个模特儿
s New Roman} I'm also a model.
你们怎么可以这样对我 靠!
How can you do it to me? Damn!
小心!
Watch out!
你们在干嘛?
Roman} What the hell are you doing?
...可恶
...Damn it!
我就说太阳那么大会晒黑
\fs20\fnTimes New Roman} I've told them that they would get a sunburn,
他们就是不听 我有什么办
but they didn't listen to me. What can I do?
你什么都说没关系
imes New Roman} You always say it doesn't matter,
然后又什么都要我负责
20\fnTimes New Roman} but ask me to be responsible for everything.
你这样到底要我怎么做?
s20\fnTimes New Roman} What do you want me to do?
喂!
Hey!
你在我的厕所抽烟?
You smoked in my bathroom?
你不怕我跟你们经理讲吗?
Aren't you afraid of I telling your manager?
漆喷一喷就好了还贴 这么费工
Just paint it. Don't waste your time.
来 好了...
OK, it's done...
阿公!来了!
Grandpa, he's here!
第一天上班就这么晚到
Late for work on the first day.
你不是一样
Aren't you the same?
几点了还不上学?
Still here. Aren't you late for school?
从恒春工商那边先跑
Go National Heng-Chun Vocational High School first.
走恒南路到国中 北门路到国小
Then take Hengnan Rd. to Junior High School.
And take Beimen Rd. to Elementary School,
走中正路接新兴路
take Zhongzheng Rd. and then Xinxing Rd..
这个要退回的 明天回去交给柜台
This should be returned to the sender. Give it back to the receptionist tomorrow.
有什么不清楚吗?
Any questions?
就这样啦 快去吧!
That's it. Go!
不然要送到半夜了
Or you have to work till midnight.
喂 这包你没拿
Hey, you forget this!
干!稳死的!
F**k, court death!
死猴崽子 第一天就晚一个多小时
Jerk, more than an hour late on the first day!
哭么!把我扶出来 给我丢在这里
Damn! Took me out and left me here.
哪里来的?
Where are you from?
邮局的摩托车撞坏了在修理啦
Post office's motor was smashed and is being repaired.
他妈的 我还以为你哑巴
F**k, I thought you were dumb.
为什么不戴安全帽?
Why don't you wear the helmet?
驾照行照拿出来
Take out your driving license.
那个呢?
What about him?
那个?
And them?
还有这个!
And her!
还闯红灯!
She even drives through the red light!
那么多人没戴 为什么抓我一个?
So many people don't wear helmets. Why just catch me?
因为你看起来比较倒霉
Cause you look in bad luck.
驾照!
Driving license!
没带驾照是不是?
Didn't bring it?
再多开一条无照驾驶
And driving without license.
叫什么名字?
What's your name?
你叫什么名字?
我操他妈的你叫什么名字?
What the f**k is your name?
不要脸!
What a cheek!
干!
F**k!
靠 摔我...
Damn，beat me...
我打死你!
I'll beat you to death!
你干什么?
What're you doing?
你在干什么!
What the hell are you doing!
劳马 你给我住手!
Rauma, stop it!
让我好好修理他
Let me teach him a lesson!
你以为你还是霹雳小组喔!
You're not in SWAT team anymore!
你给我过来!
Come here!
对不起...
Sorry, sorry...
你 你去指挥交通...
You, go directing the traffic...
他妈的!
Damn it!
什么啊?
What the f**k?
对不起...
Sorry...
他最近心情不好...
He's in bad temper these days...
你有没有怎样?
Are you OK?
讲不听耶你啊...
Why don't you listen to me...
不要这样啦!
Stop it!
不要...不要这样啦!
Come on... stop doing it!
怎样?
What's wrong?
发不动啦!
The engine is out of work!
你这很难搞喔!
It's tricky to repair it.
怎么贴成这样?
Why is it wrapped like this?
还敞篷的
Wow, it's convertible!
有我们的信吗?
Are there our mails?
没有啦!
No!
是能不能修理?
Can you repair it or not?
工具都在里面
All the tools are inside.
那你去拿呀!
Then go and get them!
钥匙在老板那边
My boss keeps the keys.
你刚回来的吗?
You returned just now?
你老板是什么时候来啊?
When will your boss come?
他就住在里面啊!
He lives inside!
是不会按电铃喔!
Then why don't you ring the bell?
阿弥陀佛 这位菩萨...
Amitabha, this bodhisattva...
阿弥陀佛 我不是土虱
Amitabha, I’m not Louse.（the same voice as bodhisattva in their language）
我叫做水蛙 我没钱!
I'm Frog. I have no money!
什么我接你的!
I replace you?
玩政治我是比你还久呢!
I've been in politics longer than you!
我接你的?
I replace you?
本来这镇长是我让你先做的...
I let you be mayor first...
镇长抱歉 这份人家赶着要盖章
Excuse me, mayor, this needs your seal now.
你先放到我的桌上
Put it on my desk.
放着就好...
Alright, put it there...
盖章...哪有那么多章要盖?
Seal...are there really so many documents that need seals?
日本歌手海滩演唱会
Japanese singer's beach concert
你如果要做镇长就要先学盖章
If you want to be a mayor, you should learn how to affix seals first.
镇长 这个你如果盖下去
Mayor, if you affix on it,
我们整个代表会是不会放过你喔!
all our representatives will not let up off!
友子
Tomoko...
请原谅我这个懦弱的男人
Please forgive my cowardice.
从来不敢承认我们两人的相爱
I never dared to admit we were in love.
我甚至已经忘记
I even forget...
我是如何迷上那个不照规定理发
how I became obsessed with you.
而惹得我大发雷霆的女孩了
The girl who never had the right hair-cut and angered me.
友子
Tomoko...
你固执不讲理 爱玩爱流行
You were a stubborn girl who liked playing and fashion,
我却如此受不住的迷恋你
but I couldn't help being infatuated with you
只是好不容易你毕业了
Finally, you graduated ...
我们却战败了
but my country lost the war.
我是战败国的子民
I'm the vanquished.
贵族的骄傲瞬间堕落为犯人的枷
My pride in aristocratism suddenly became our fetter.
我只是个穷教师
I am but a poor teacher,
为何要背负一个民族的罪
Why should I bear the crime of a country?
时代的宿命是时代的罪过
A epoch's destiny is the epoch's crime.
我只是个穷教师
I'm nothing but a poor teacher.
我爱你 却必须放弃你
I love you, but I have to leave you.
天父上帝阮齐声...
Oh, lord, let us pray together...
赞美称呼你尊名
and bless your name.
阿...
A...
...们
...men.
诸位兄姐 这时我们同心低头来祷告
Every body, let us bow our heads and pray together.
马拉桑!
Malasun!
小姐小姐 你好你好
Miss, how are you?
我跟你们黄主任有约
I have an appointment with director Huang.
可不可以帮我联络一下
Can you call him, please.
你稍等
Wait a second, please.
喂 请接一下黄主任
Hello, is director Huang available now?
小姐 这是一个全新的品牌
Miss, this is a completely new brand.
把原住民的小米酒重新包装
We repackage the aborigines' millet wine.
我们准备打入国际市场
We plan to make inroad into the international market.
千年传统 全新感受
Thousands years of history, completely new feelings.
这酒叫马拉桑
The wine is called Malasun.
我先倒一杯给你喝喝看
Let me get you a drink to try.
不要不要...
No thanks...
喂 主任 这有一位...
Yes, director, here I have a Mr....
马拉桑!马...拉...桑
Malasun! Ma...La...Sun
马拉桑先生说跟你有约
Mr. Malasun says that he has an appointment with you.
好...B1办公室
Ok...the office B1
B1 好好好...
B1, ok, alright...
你从那边坐电梯下去就可以了
You can take elevator there.
你们总经理呢?
Where is your general manager?
你...
You...
代表...什么事情啊?
Mr. Representative, can I help you?
那边坐一下嘛!代表!
Have a seat there, Mr. Representative!
情是什么玩意
What is love?
只不过是玩玩而已
It's nothing but a game.
Honey、darling、baby
Honey, darling, baby
或是叫我小亲亲
or call me sweetie.
你要到几楼?
Which floor?
地下室!
The basement!
年轻人不会走楼梯啊!
Can't you young man walk?
你没脚吗?
You have no legs?
五楼!
Fifth floor!
喔 爱你爱到不怕死
Oh, I'm not scared of death cause I love you.
但你若劈腿 就去死一死
But if you have someone else, then go to hell.
喔...爱你爱到不怕死baby
Oh...I'm not scared of death cause I love you baby.
爱我请你让我疯狂一次
Please indulge me if you love me.
阿...们...
A...men...
谁说咱们恒春没人才
Who says our Hengchun has no talents.
大大你...怎么...
Dada, why are you here?
礼拜结束了吗?
The church has finished?
还没啊!
Not yet!
那你怎么在这?
Then why are you here?
上帝把我赶出来的
God kicked me out.
代表 什么事情气成这样
Mr. Representative, what made you so angry?
饭店你的 海我们管的啦!
The hotel is yours, but the sea is ours!
以为有钱就什么都BOT
You think you can do everything with money by BOT?
别这么说啦 什么你们的 我们的
Don't say so. What's yours and ours?
现在时代在进步 要有国际观念
The time is in progress. We must have a global outlook now.
要有地球村的观念
It's a global village.
什么地球村?
What global village?
你们外地人来这里开饭店 做经理
You outsiders come here, build hotels and be managers.
土地要BOT 山也BOT
The land's BOT and mountains are BOT.
连海也要给我BOT
Now even the sea is planned to BOT.
我们在地人呢?都出外当人家伙计
What about our natives? All work outside for other people.
-这像住同一颗地球上吗? -喂...
-Does this seem like living in the same Earth?  -Hey...
代表你要去哪?
Mr. Representative, where are you going?
这间啦!
This one!
不会开门喔!
Open the door!
这面海这么漂亮
The sea's so beautiful.
我们自己却看不到
Why can’t our own people enjoy it?
这是为什么?
Why?
因为有钱人连海都买去了
Because rich people bought it,
却不留一点给我们
but left us nothing.
每年我们恒春都在春天呐喊
Every year Spring Scream is held in Hengchun.
我们在地人呢?
What about our natives?
有什么享受?
What enjoyment do we get?
有啦 在台下跟着吱吱叫
We can just cheer with others.
最大的福利 就是捡垃圾
The biggest welfare we get is rubbish everywhere.
拜托 春天呐喊跟我们又没关系
Come on, Spring Scream has nothing to do with us
这回我们从日本请来的
This year we invite
是真正出名的那个叫什么...
a famous singer from Japan named what...
疗伤歌手啦!
...healing singer!
那歌声像大海...
His voice is like the sea...
我不管你请来的日本歌星
I don't care the Japanese singer you invited
是要当医生还是要当船员
is coming to be a doctor or a sailor.
我跟你要的
What I am asking for...
是暖场的乐团要找我们在地人
is to have a local warm up band.
你是听不懂喔?
Can't you understand?
可是你们在地就没乐团啊!
But you have no local band!
我这一场 要给他办的很热闹
This time I want to make it high.
所以我们要请很热闹的乐团
So we invite this rock band.
你们这就没有这样的人才
You have no such talents here.
你现在在说什么?
What are you talking about?
还分你们 我们?
What you and we?
你刚刚不是说不要分
What about the "global village" you mentioned just now?
什么意思啊?
What do you mean?
我是说...
I mean...
好啦...不管怎样
Alright...anyway,
我就是可以从在地这里
I promise I can get...
找出一个够水准的乐团给你
a local band that lives up your standard.
不可能啦!
It's impossible!
有可能啦!
It's possible!
Possible!
跟你说有可能就有可能啦!
I say it's possible!
要不然我们明年一起来选镇长
Or let's run for the town mayor next year.
看谁选的上?
Wait and see who will be elected.
拜托 你别这样嘛!
Come on, please!
台北那边我跟人家都已经谈好了
I've promised those people in Taipei.
辞掉不就好了!
Just lay them off!
钱都付了 要怎么给人家辞掉?
The money has been paid, how to lay them off?
-是啊! -我跟你说 没关系!
-Yeah!  -Listen, it's all right!
假使连个表演乐团都不留给在地人
Our local band can't even get a chance to perform.
就算是要绑架镇长、绑架县长
Even if I have to kidnap the the town and the country mayor,
我也不会让你这个活动在海边表演
I'll never let your concert be held at beach.
我们走啦
Let's go.
慢着...
Wait...
主席 你让我拜托一下好不好
Mr. Representative, do me a favor please?
我这次花了多少钱你知道吗?
Do you know how much I spend this time?
我还请了很多外国的模特儿
I invite many foreign models
来给人照相宣传
for photographic promo.
这叫做整体行销 你知道吗?
This is called total marketing, you know?
我跟你说 我决定明年要选镇长
Listen, I decide to run for the town mayor next year.
你考虑看看 一分钟!
You have one minute to consider!
主席 你听过中孝介吗?
Mr. Representative, have you ever heard of Kousuke Atari?
人话你听不懂耶!
You really don't understand human language, do you?
等等 慢点
Wait, hold on!
好啦!
All right!
用你们的团啦
Then use your band...
Use your band...
咱们的团啦
That's our band...
咱们的团啦 咱这团
It's our band...our band!
马...拉...桑
Ma...La...Sun.
试试看
Have a try...
怎么样 有没有感觉酒香在嘴里?
How do you feel? Do you feel the bouquet?
...芬芳的感觉
...it has a fragrant flavor.
哇 好酒量 女中豪杰!
Wow! You're really a big drinker...Bravo!
我再倒一杯给你
Let me give you another drink.
为什么?
Why?
好 我马上去
Alright, I'll go right now.
喂
Hey, hey!
啊 要走了耶!
Ah? They are leaving!
好 我马上
OK, I'll go!
干什么?
What the hell are you doing?
我也是模特儿
I'm a model too.
为什么你都不找我走秀?
Why do you never ask me for shows?
老是要我做保姆做翻译呢?
Why you always let me do nursing and interpreting work?
好 我知道
Alright, I got it...
只是现在时尚的潮流就是不适合
It's just because you doesn't fit the current fashion.
其实你的型很OK
Actually you look very OK.
你还年轻好不好?
You're still young, OK?
我老了
I'm old!
我已经被你气老了
My anger for you has made me old!
我学校毕业后还愿意留在台湾
I chose to stay in Taiwan after graduation
就是因为你跟我说我很有特色
because you told me I was special.
现在你反而说我不流行
Now you say I'm not in fashion
只能当个翻译
and can only be an interpreter?
大小姐你就帮帮忙好不好?
Missy, help me this time please.
这个案子很突然
This case comes abruptly,
但机会却是很难得呀
but it's now or never!
日本的唱片公司他们不相信
The record company of Japan doesn't believe that
他们可以在恒春那个地方
they can find good bandsmen
找到适合的乐手
in Hengchun town.
所以我拜托你
So I'm begging you.
你就先在那边监督一下
You just supervise there for a while.
-挺一下，看一下  -不管怎样
-Have a look and give some suggestions.  -Anyway.
你不可以问都没问 就把我留下来
You can't leave me here without even asking me.
不可以这样子的
You can't do this.
友子小姐的房卡
The room card of Miss Tokomo.
你也知道日本人做事就是最龟毛
You know Japanese are always picky,
也最难搞的啊
and most difficult to deal with.
你要讲日本人坏话时
When you're speaking ill of Japanese,
请你记得我也是个日本人好吗?
please remember I'm also a Japanese, OK?
说好的乐团干嘛变来变去?
The band has fixed, why still change!
你每天七晚八晚 散散漫漫的
You come back so late and laze away all the day.
是在干什么?
What are you doing?
我又不是在这里上班
I'm not at work here.
今天路线你自己排
You plan out today's route by yourself.
排好我再看行不行
After you finish, I'll check then.
第三天
The third day.
该怎么克制自己不去想你?
How can I stop myself from thinking about you?
你是南方艳阳下成长的学生
You're a student growing up in the bright sunshine of the South.
我是从飘雪的北方渡洋过海的老师
I'm a teacher sailing across the ocean from the snowy North.
我们是这么的不同
We're so different.
为何却会如此的相爱?
Why are we in such strong love?
我怀念艳阳 我怀念热风
I miss the bright sun and the hot wind.
我犹有记忆你被红蚁惹毛的样子
I still remember your face irritated by red ants.
我知道我不该嘲笑你
I knew I shouldn't laugh at you.
但你踩着红蚁的样子真美
But you were so beautiful when trod on the red ants.
像踩着一种奇幻的舞步
It seemed like you were dancing fantastic steps
愤怒 强烈又带着轻挑的嬉笑
Angrily and passionately with a frivolous laugh.
友子 我就是那时爱上你的
Tomoko, that's the moment when I fell in love with you.
咱城南里各位里民请注意收听
Everyone, attention please...
今天晚上七点半在镇公所活动中心
At 7:30 p.m. tonight, in the community activity center.
有一场乐器表演的挑选活动
There's an election of instrument performance.
身分证呢?
Your ID card please.
还要身分喔?
ID card?
没身分证我哪知道你是外地还在地的?
How can I know you are a native or outsider without your ID card?
闪啦 没看到跛脚喔!
Step aside! Don't you see I'm crippled?
闪 闪啦!
Step aside...step aside!
这小孩都说不听 闪一边去啦!
These kids don't listen, get out of my way!
翔翔你要自己吃喔!
Xiangxiang, you need to eat on your own!
十号 好啊
Number ten, alright...
好啦
OK, no problem...
翔翔最乖 自己吃喔
Good boy, Xiangxiang, eat by yourself!
老板娘 我朋友刚刚帮我报名
Mrs. boss, my friend has just signed me up for an activity.
要到活动中心表演打鼓
I need to go to the community center to play the drums.
好啊 要去你就去啊
Alright, just go if you want!
你要不要来看我表演
Would you like to see my performance?
我去 这三个小孩子谁照顾?
Me? Then who will take care of these three kids?
活动中心小孩子可以进去啊
Kids are allowed to enter the community center too!
-要去吗  -好
-Do you want to go?    - Yes!
你 别跑!
You, stop running...
别跑啊...
Stop!
请你的镇民们安静点好吗?
Can you ask your people to be quiet, please?
不要吵!
Keep it down!
安静啦!
Be quite!
安静没听到?
Be quiet! Don't you hear me?
那三个孩子是谁的?
Whose kids are those three?
带出去啦!
Take them out!
鸭尾 阿公跟你讲
Yawei, let me tell you...
人家在表演 还这样大小声
Speaking loudy when somebody is performing,
没礼貌
it's rude!
茂伯啊
Uncle Mao!
怎么这么快就完了
So quickly?
结束了吗?
Finished?
鼓掌啊!
Applaud!
十号，换你表演了
No.10, it's your turn
十号 哭爸 是我啦!
No.10? Oh my god, that's me!
十号 十号
No.10...No.10...
香肠的 拜托 帮我顾一下
Please, look after them for a while!
十号
No.10...
十号!
No.10!
你干嘛?
What's wrong with you?
十号 十号啦
No.10, I'm No.10!
搞什么水乱喷
What the hell are you doing! You spray water on me?
抱歉
I'm sorry.
这不是水 是口水
This is not water. It's saliva.
你很肮脏耶!
You're sick!
我还以为你不来了
I didn't expect you would come.
拿去.
Take it
不然我摔烂它
Or I will smash it.
你摔看看
Have a try.
有胆子你摔看看
If you dare.
看到没有?
You see?
我们恒春的鼓开工了啦!
The drum of our Hengchun starts working!
跟着
Follow me.
你有报名吗?
Did you sign up?
不会中
It won't hit...
就跟你说不会中你怕什么?
Told you it won't hit. Why are you afraid?
喂，送信的
Hey, postman.
弹吉他是一件很快乐的事
Playing the guitar is a pleasant thing.
茂伯 不要来乱啦!
Uncle Mo, please don't rock the boat!
收起来啦
Put it away...
我老婆和你老爸都很早就死了
My wife and your dad have passed away for a long time.
我几个孩子都出外在工作
My children are all working outside.
你几个兄弟也都出门在外
So do your brothers.
只剩我和你妈一个人
Only your mother and I are left here.
很孤单呢!
We are lonely!
房子是那么大间
The house is so large.
床又那么大顶
The bed is so big.
拜托好不好
Oh, please.
讲到房子就已经火大了，还讲到床
It's burned me up that you mentioned the house, but you even mentioned the bed.
人家教会牧师也说了
The priest of church has said that,
一个人不好
it's not good to be alone.
他们的上帝才会又创造了女人
So their god created a woman after a man.
人本来就是要相互在一起嘛!
People should be together.
我话就说到这里
I've finished all I need to say.
希望你能体谅
Hope you can understand!
只有这个人会打鼓?
Only he can play the drum?
不能因为只有一个会打鼓就叫他打
You can't let him play just because he's the only one.
他打的不好是不是?
You don't think he plays well?
表演不是好不好的问题
Performance is not about good or bad.
而是舞台魅力
It's a matter of charms on stage.
可是
But...
他长得跟昆虫一样
He looks like an insect.
什么昆虫?
What insect?
都还没开始，水蛙看成蟾蜍
It hasn't stated yet while you take the frog for toad.
水蛙
Nice to meet you, my name is Frog.
今天晚上七点半饭店地下室练打鼓
You come to basement of the hotel to practice this 7:30 pm.
千挑万选才选到你的
You're handpicked from many people.
不要给我漏气
Don't let me down.
记得 放感情去打知不知道?
Remember, put your emotion in when playing.
加油啊!
Come on!
这原住民吹口琴不错啊!
This native plays the harmonica pretty well!
摇滚乐团吹口琴谁听得见啊?
Who can hear the harmonica in a rock band?
谁说的 人家昨天又打鼓
Who says, they played the drum,
又弹吉他又吹口琴，很好听耶!
while playing the guitar and harmonica yesterday. It sounded good!
那个每个人都 哇 拍拍手!
Everyone...wow, applaud!
不然就叫这个弹贝斯啊!
Otherwise, ask him to play the bass.
吹口琴的怎么会弹贝斯?
How can a harmonica player play the bass?
哭夭!
Bullshit!
弹贝斯和吹口琴不是一样DoReMi
Aren't playing the bass and harmonica both about DoReMi?
会吹那个就会弹那个啦!
If you can play this then you can play that too!
你以为我不懂音乐喔?
Don't you think I understand music?
你是来乱的是不是?
You come to make troubles, don't you?
你负责弹贝斯 你儿子弹吉他
You play the bass, and your son plays the guitar.
我不会弹贝斯啊
I don't know how to play the bass.
没关系啦，去了就会了
It doesn't matter, you can learn it there.
好啦，反正就这样决定了啦
Alright, it's finally settled then!
那主唱
What about the lead singer...
主唱就叫代表主席 他那个啦
The lead singer? We can ask Mr. Representative’s...uh...you know who.
等一下 那个那个是谁?
Wait...you know who? Who's that?
昨天有来吗
Did he come yesterday?
就昨天弹吉他弹到翻脸那个啦!
The one who got angry when played the guitar yesterday!
那个会唱歌喔?
He can sing?
你真的很看不起人耶!
You really have no respect for others.
人家之前在台北乐团也是主唱耶
He once was the lead singer of a Taipei band!
会写 会弹 又会唱
He can write, play and sing.
这人才你是去哪里找啊?
Where else can you find such a talent?
你是来乱的是不是?
You come to make troubles, don't you?
我有说话吗?
Did I say anything?
你没看到男人在那里讨论
Don't you see men discussing here?
你女生在那边啧啧啧
You such a girl make noises there all the time.
你牙齿痛 牙齿痛不会看医生喔!
Do you have a toothache? If you do, why not go to the dentist?
不用管她啦 来 继续
Let her go. Come on, let's continue.
这弹键盘的太老了 都欧巴桑了
The keyboardist's too old, she's already an Oba-san.
太老 不然就这个 这个40岁
Too old?How about this one? He's 40.
你看我们的海这么漂亮
Look, our sea is so beautiful.
为什么一些年轻人就是留不住?
Why can't it retain those young people?
友子，你看我们的海
Tomoko, look, our sea...
我听不懂台语
I can't understand Taiwanese!
抱歉
I'm sorry...
妹妹 晚上七点夏都酒店
Little girl,go to Chateau Beach Resort at 7 p.m.
你代表我们恒春参加乐团
You'll play in the band on behalf of our Hengchun town.
我阿公呢 我阿公有被选到吗?
How about my grandpa? Is he chosen?
拜托 我们这是摇滚乐
Oh please, it's rock and roll.
你们茂伯是弹月琴的
Your grandpa Uncle Mao plays the yu-kin.
死猴崽子
You wretched child!
马拉桑
Malasun!
马 马上什么啦?
Ma...Ma what?
不是马上 是马拉桑!
It's Malasun!
哭夭 现在七点半了
Oh shit, it's already 7:30!
弹到九点 要弹给鬼听
You guys play till 9 p.m. who will hear?
别说那么多 叫你们经理来跟我讲
Stop the crap, ask your manager to talk with me.
水蛙
Hey, Frog.
-有没有带感情出来  -有
-Do you take your emotion with you?   -Yes!
用感情下去打 知道吗
Put your emotion into the drum, will you?
你们也都有喔
You are all here huh?
水蛙啦水蛙
I'm Frog, Frog.
鼓手鼓手啦
I'm the drummer!
水蛙啦
I'm Frog!
-你好  -水蛙
-Nice to meet you...   -I'm Frog!
你什么时候回来的?
When did you come back?
我女儿
This is my daughter.
好可爱唷
She's so cute!
你别惹她
Don't piss her off...
我鼓手 你妈的老同学
I'm the drummer, your mother's old classmate.
你好 我是鼓手水蛙
Hello, I'm drummer Frog.
你这只昆虫 还不快给我现出原形!
You insect, show me your true color right now!
对不起（日文）
Excuse me.
我们阿嘉呢?
Where is our lead singer Aga?
去问神啊!
Ask the god!
好了 不用等了 你们自己练
Alright, don't wait any longer, you practice by yourselves!
要练什么 今天第一天呢
Practice what? This is the first day!
是啊 也没有谱 大家也都不熟
Yes, there's no music score, and we're not familiar with each other yet.
你好，我叫洪国荣
Nice to meet you, my name is Hung Kuo-jung.
我就是代表会主席
I'm the chairman of the town council!
你好 我鼓手 我叫水蛙
Nice to meet you, I'm the drummer, Frog.
我知道啦 你是我选的啦!
I know! It's me who chose you!
我是代表会主席 身高170
I'm the chairman of town council, 1.7 meters tall,
体重75，今年60岁
75 kilograms weight and 60 years old.
我最大的兴趣
My biggest hobby
就是吵架 打架 杀人 放火
is quarreling, fighting, murdering and burning.
而我最大的心愿
As for my biggest wish?
就是把整个恒春放火烧掉
I hope I can burn the whole Hnegchun town out.
然后把所有年轻人
Then ask all the young people
叫回自己家乡 重新再造
to come back to their hometown for reconstruction.
自己做老板 别出外当人家伙计
They can be their own boss rather than go outside and be others' clerks
这样我们熟悉了吗?
So are we familiar now?
有啦 会痛啦!
Yes, yes! It hurts!
主席 好了 别生气
Mr. Representative, alright, don't be angry.
好了 别生气啦
That's OK, don't get angry...
你也有讲啊
You've said something too!
楼下在干嘛 练团?
What are they doing downstairs? Band practicing?
马拉桑先生
Mr. Malasun.
以后可不可以请你讲话小声一点?
Could you please lower your voice a little bit?
吓死人啊你
You scared me!
拿去!
Take it!
一个酒杯这么多人喝 有没有洗?
All people use a same cup, have you washed it?
是的
Yes!
他们已经开始练习了
They've started practicing.
是这样啊
Ah, I see!
我过两天再将情形跟你报告好吗?
I'll report the details to you in a few days, alright?
台北公司我已经说过了
I've talked with the Taipei company!
是的
Yes.
是的，我知道了
Alright, I see.
你搞什么?
What the hell are you doing?
忽快忽慢的
Sometimes fast and sometimes slow.
来闹的啊?
Are you playing pranks here?
讲电话出去好不好!
Get out when talking on the phone!
你一天一天越摆越靠过来
You're putting it closer and closer.
今天干脆直接摆在柜台旁边啊?
It's simply next to the front desk today.
你过不过份啊你?
Don't go overboard!
马拉桑!
Malasun!
我跟你们总经理有约...
I have an appointment with your general manager...
代表...
Mr. Representative...
我保力那边的客家人 名片在这
I'm Hakka from Baoli, this is my card.
这是我们公司和信义乡农会
Our company and farmers'association of Xinyi Township.
合作的新产品小米酒
jointly produces this millet wine.
叫做马拉桑
It's called Malasun.
千年传统 全新感受
Thousand years of history, completely new feelings.
这瓶送你 试试看!
This one is for you. Have a try!
他已经在楼上等你了 请你上楼
He's been waiting for you upstairs, please.
谢谢
Thank you!
代表...
Mr. Representative...
现在整个恒春 只有我一个业务
I'm the only salesman in Hengchun.
我想说可不可以帮个忙
Could you please do me a favor,
介绍我去别家饭店
and introduce me to other hotels?
因为这次我们的产品
Because my boss required that our products
我们老板想要走高级路线
should adhere to the high-end principle.
拜托一下，拜托...
Please, please...
你保力是车城
Boli's in Checheng Town.
我这里是恒春
Here is Hengchun Town.
我为什么要帮你?
Why should I help you?
少年人 有志气一点
Young man, be aspiring.
不要一天到晚为了赚钱去捧人LP
Don't bootlick others for money.
还好 还不错
So-so, not bad.
目前每天都盯着他们在练习新歌
I've been urging them practicing new songs everyday.
是的 第一首歌会在这周练好
Yes, we'll finish practicing the first song this week.
第二首歌也会在周末前做出来
The second one will be created by this weekend.
天气疯了 海水滚了
Weather has gone mad and the sea has been boiled.
所以我要无乐不作
So I want to do everything about happiness.
不要浪费每一刻，快乐
Don't waste every happy moment.
当梦的天行者...
Fly your dream bravely.
停停...
Stop...
怎样?
Why?
这边我还要加个东西
I want to add something here.
当梦的天行者
Fly your dream bravely.
阿...们...
A...men...
好啦 随便啦 你们高兴就好了
Fine, whatever, do as you please.
再来一个!
Once more!
-天是空的...  -等一下...
-the sky is empty...  -hold on...
刚才那个结束之后
After that,
我再试一个更好玩的 来!
I'll try something more fun, come on!
喂!
Hey!
能不能从头到尾走过一遍再发表意见
Can you give suggestions after we finish the whole song?
到现在都已经三天了
It has been three days,
都还没从头到尾走过一遍
but we haven't sang the song completely.
你啦 弹键盘的
You! The keyboardist!
速度忽快忽慢
Sometimes fast and sometimes slow.
贝斯手永远跟不上节拍
The bassist can never keep the beat.
鼓手的意见又这么多
The drummer has so many opinions.
到底想怎样 要不要练啊?
What on earth do you want? Practice or not?
是怎样啦?是怎样啦?
What? What?
你瞧不起我们就对了
You just look down on us.
你弹的最好就对了啦!
You’re the best, ok?
每次都只能你有意见
Only you can give opinions.
不然你想怎么样?
What do you want?
怎么样 你想摔是不是?
What? You wanna fight?
有三件事我想讲
I'll say three points.
第一 我觉得弹键盘的太小了
First, the keyboardist is too young.
弹贝斯的又太老了
while the bassist is too old.
我希望这两个人一定要再找过
These two people must be replaced.
第二 我觉得你们现在真是一团乱
Second, you're in a mess now.
一定要增加练习时间
You must practice more.
第三!
Third!
日本公司那边希望我们有两首歌
The Japanese wants us to sing two songs.
但是，到现在我只听到一首而已
Till now, we get only one.
而且这首歌还是你很久以前写的
that you wrote long time ago.
不过 重点是另外一首
however, what matters is the other song.
行不行啊
Can you write it or not?
不行你能解决吗
Can you fix it up if I can't?
我又不是团长
I'm not the leader.
撞死你!
Go to the hell!
阿嘉
Aga
你每天都送信送到几点?
When do you finish work every day?
差不多五点吧
Almost 5 p.m..
五点喔!
5 p.m.!
你这个新来的手脚算快嘛!
You are fast as a green hand!
你信丟信箱丟深一点 别让人拿走
Put the letters deep inside the mailbox, don't let others get the letters.
最近有人在反应信都收不到
Many people complain that they lose letters recently.
喂，女孩子
Hey, girl.
你要找谁吗
Who are you looking for?
对不起，请问阿嘉住在这边吗
Excuse me, dose Aga live here?
他去送信了 你要找他做什么
He's delivering letters! Why do you find him?
他可能下午才会回来喔
He won't be back until the afternoon.
我是饭店乐团的联络人
I'm the liaison of the hotel's band.
我有一张CD要让他当作曲的参考
I want to give him a CD as reference when he composes.
麻烦你帮我拿给他好吗
Could you please give it to him?
喔 你就是那个日本女孩子
Oh, you are that Japanese girl?
来...进来里面坐!进来...
Come...come in..
不用...我写张字条给他就好了
No, thanks... I'll leave him a note.
你真的不进来坐?
You really don't come in?
不用...
No, thanks.
你日本人写我们中文
As a Japanese, your written Chinese
写得这么漂亮喔...
is so beautiful.
抱歉...有没有怎样
Sorry... Are you all right?
不小心催到油门的
I goosed the throttle mistakenly.
捡槟榔哩...
I was picking up the areca-nut.
你怎么了...
Are you ok?
我没有怎么样...
I’m fine.
怎么样
Are you all right?
我的眼睛看不见
I can’t see.
把它擦掉，卫生纸啦!我看不到...
Wipe the blood. I can't see...
你来扶他一下
Help him up.
我的脚没有问题!
My legs are fine!
上车啦!
Get on!
擦干净啦!
Wipe it up!
请问一下，那个...
Excuse me, that...
谢谢
Thank you!
怎样啦 手有没有受伤
What happened? Do the hands get hurt?
哭夭!
Shit!
鼻子怎么贴成这样
What happened to the nose?
就已经在衰了 还给他打叉!
He is already unlucky, you still put an X on his nose!
他伤在这里...
His wound is right here.
贴横的中眼睛 贴直的中鼻头
The adhesive tape should avoid the eyes and the nose area.
我哪有办法?
I have no other choice.
笑什么啦 人家在难过了还笑!
Don’t laugh. He’s so upset, how can you laugh!
这楼梯这么陡要怎么爬
The staircase is so steep.
你这样叮叮咚咚 弹也弹不成调
You play turnless music.
这样也行喔?
Can you do it?
那个不是啦!
Those are not letters.
阿嘉!
Aga!
阿嘉...
Aga...
拜托一下 你不要讲啦!
Please, don't tell anyone else!
年轻人不懂事 你就帮忙送一下
He is still young. Why don’t you help him?
我吃饱太闲?
I have nothing better to do?
我这么老了又跛脚 还要帮你送?
I’ m old and limping, and I still have to help him deliver letters?
我再三的交代 你还这样乱搞
I told you repeatedly, you still don’t take it seriously.
如果人家结婚 生子
What if it's the message about getting married, or giving birth
或是出殡的通知怎么办?
or even holding a funeral?
现在都打电话了 哪有人写信
Now everyone uses phones, who will write letters?
哭夭啊!
Shit!
你是在邮局还是在电信局啊?
Are you working in the post office or telephone office?
茂伯 你不要说...
Uncle Mao, Please don’t tell others...
别这样...我没有缺钱!
Don’t...I don’t need money!
看你喜欢什么就去买嘛
Buy whatever you like!
我就爱弹琴啊!
I like playing music!
爱弹琴就去买新的琴嘛
Buy a new instrument then!
我弹琴要弹给谁听?
Who do I play for?
现在什么时代了
Nowadays,
还有人听我们这些老的弹琴?
who still wanna listen to us old men playing music?
报纸都报说我是国宝
The newspaper says I’m national treasure.
宝个芋仔番薯啦 谁在稀罕?
That's bullshit! Who cares me?
像我们这种国宝就要出去让人欣赏
People like me should go out and be admired as national treasure.
不是放在家里当神主牌
rather than stay at home.
好啦...
All right...
就几百张信没送 应该不会处份太重
Just hundreds of letters, the punishment won't be too severe.
以前还听过给人家偷拆信被判刑的
I heard someone was sentenced for opening other's letters.
就跟你说过这不是啦!
I told you it's not!
不然那是什么
What's it then?
黄色的?
Porno?
对啦...
Yeah...
多希望这时有暴风
How I wish a storm would come now,
把我淹没在这台湾与日本间的海域
and drown me in the sea between Taiwan and Japan.
这样我就不必为了我的懦弱负责
Then I don't need to be responsible for my cowardice.
友子
Tomoko,
才几天的航行
I’m just sailing for several days.
海风所带来的哭声
The weeps brought by the sea wind
已让我苍老许多
have made me old already.
我不愿离开甲板
I don’t want to leave the deck,
也不愿睡觉
or go to bed.
我心里已经做好盘算
I have made up my mind.
一旦让我着陆
Once I land,
我将一辈子不愿再看见大海
I won’t see the sea anymore.
海风啊 为何总是带来哭声呢
Sea wind, why do you always bring weeps?
爱人哭、嫁人哭
They weep for loving, for marrying
生孩子哭
or for having babies.
想着你未来可能的幸福我总是会哭
I always cry when I think of you marrying someone else.
只是我的泪水
But my tears
总是在涌出前就被海风吹干
is dried by the sea wind before they drop.
涌不出泪水的哭泣 让我更苍老了
I cry without tear, which makes me even older.
可恶的风
Hateful wind,
可恶的月光
Hateful moonlight,
可恶的海
Hateful sea.
我上次就跟你讲过
I told you last time,
弹贝斯的那个欧吉桑太老了
the bassist's too old.
你今天又换来一个更老的!
Now you get a much older one!
人又不是我找的，关我什么事?
I don't ask him to come. It's none of my business.
乐团又不是我负责
I'm not in charge of the band.
你不负责?
You aren't in charge?
好 那到时我看你在台上怎么唱!
Fine, I'll see how you are going to sing on the stage!
我爱我的妹妹呀!
I love you my little sister!
哥哥真爱你
I love you so much.
那当时在公园里
When in park at that time,
怎么了你可知
do you know what was going on?
看见月色渐渐亮...
I saw the moonlight brighten gradually.
你...
You...
你真的让他拿那个当贝斯吗
Do you really let him be the bassist?
那个老头 我敢打赌
That geezer, I bet
他从出生到现在一定没有拿过贝斯
he's never touched a bass since he was born.
还有几天日本歌手就要来了
The Japanese singer will come here soon.
怎么办
What should we do?
还有你的第二首歌呢
What about your second song?
连个影子都还没有!
I haven’t seen even a note!
我给你的CD你听了吗
Did you listen to the CD I gave you?
你看 他这样!
Look, look at him!
不要跟我说作曲不是你负责的!
Don't tell me you are not in charge of composing!
干什么啊?
What are you doing?
你看!
Look!
盐巴!
Salt!
他做不出曲子还有空去海边玩水
He had time to go to the sea, but didn't have time to compose.
你每天迟到
You've been late everyday.
我都以为你在作曲才没有说你
I didn't criticize you as I thought you were composing,
原来你跑到海边玩水
but actually you were playing on the beach.
你们不要太过分!
Don't push me too far!
我不干了!
I quit!
走开啦!
Get out of my way!
你怎么都不讲话啦!
Why did you say nothing!
他讲哪一国中文你听得懂啊
Can you understand her Chinese?
喔 日本人什么都敢吃!
Wow, the Japanese dares to eat everything!
看见月色渐渐亮
I saw the moonlight brighten gradually.
有话对你讲
I have something to tell you.
妹妹妳呀想一想
My little sister, you think about it.
要干什么
What do you want to do?
你弹这支...
You play this one...
这哪边是头啊
How to play this?
喂 你就这样走啦?
Hey, are you leaving?
喂，你这个日本人
Hey, you Japanese.
答应的事怎么可以没做到就离开!
How can you leave without finishing your work!
友子小姐...你怎么了
Miss Tomoko... What's wrong?
友子小姐...
Miss Tomoko...
友子小姐
Miss Tomoko,
这是我弟弟的长孙今天娶媳妇
the grandson of my young brother is getting married today.
晚上在庙口有酒席
We have a wedding reception this evening.
请和我们一起同高兴吧!
Please come and join us!
今晚请一起来吧!
Please come tonight!
恭喜
Congratulations!
我是乐团弹贝斯的
I'm the bassist of the band.
今天闲着想说来练一下
I'm free today so I come here to practice.
主席 你看!
Mr. Representative, look!
这个客家人这么拼
This Hakka works so hard.
晚上顾饭店 白天跑店面
He works day and night.
苍蝇找狗屎啦!
What he can is to be diligent!
你看人家今天跑的外务
The bottles of millet wine he sells today
比他们阿嘉堆在家里的信还多!
is more than the letters at Aga's.
干!
Shit!
没事啦...
All right...
嘿 马拉桑!
Hey! Malasun!
夏都你好 是
Hello, Chateau Beach Resort. Can I help you?
60瓶?
Sixty bottles?
好好...谢谢...拜拜!
OK! OK...thank you...bye!
我再弹一次给你听...
Let me show you once again...
这样也不对 那样也不对
This is wrong, and that is wrong.
什么都不对!
How can I do it right!
马拉桑!
Malasun!
干什么啦!
What are you dong!
我教你弹...
I teach you...
马拉桑!你做到大生意了!
Malasun! You have a big deal!
刚刚代表主席打电话来
Mr. Representative called just now.
要你晚上准备60瓶小米酒
He asked you to prepare 60 bottles of millet wine tonight
到大庙会场喜宴!
for the wedding reception!
60...
Sixty...
不好意思...
Sorry...
60瓶啦...60瓶...
Sixty bottles...sixty bottles...
马拉桑...你跟代表主席很熟吗
Malasun... do you know Mr. Representative well?
拜托 给老人家一个机会
Please, give me old man a chance.
别说你会弹琴啦!拜托啦!
Don't tell him you can play bass, please!
马拉桑!大家好...
Malasun! Hello, everyone...
代表主席请的
It's Mr. Representative's treat.
我公司的新产品马拉桑小米酒
Our company's new product: Malasun millet wine.
阿嘉!
Aga!
来来...菜来了!
Here come the dishes!
友子小姐
Miss Tomoko,
这是阿嘉他妈妈
this is Aga’s mom.
我有看过 他来过我们家
I've seen her. She came to my house once.
那边先坐!
Please sit down!
再用力一点!
Harder!
下一位 陈光辉先生请准备
Next one is Mr. Chen Kuang-hui, please get ready.
这里...陈光辉我本人
Here...Chen Kuang-hui is me.
爸爸 头很痛很讨厌
Dad, my head aches. Stop it!
好了啦
All right.
不用扶啦!
No need to support me!
白痴
Idiot.
酒量好是不是?
Ah, you can hold your liquor well?
水蛙还包装成这样 嚣张喔
Look, Frog dresses like that!
我哪知道 我想说...
How do I know, I want to say...
那边坐...
Sit there...
这边没位子了!
There's no seat here!
不然我...坐那桌好了
Or...I can sit there.
老板娘
Hi, Mrs. Boss.
你怎么穿成这样?
Why are you dressed like this?
水蛙叔叔 你真帅!
Uncle Frog, you look handsome!
感谢林代表的歌声
Thanks for Mr. Lin’s singing.
好可爱喔
You're so cute!
给我记住 胆小鬼给我记住
You cowards, I'll bear in mind.
去...去给爸爸加油
Go...cheer for daddy.
阿志，快去给爸爸加油
Go, go...cheer for daddy.
现在来唱这首“转吧七彩霓虹灯”
I'll sing the song Turn On The Disco Ball.
你怎么会有这套
How do you get this suit?
老板又喝醉了?
Is boss drunk again?
老板娘 这送你
Mrs. Boss, this is for you.
十二月的海总是带着愤怒
In December, the sea is always filled with anger.
我承受着耻辱和悔恨的臭味
I endure the shame and regrets
陪同不安静地晃荡
accompanied with uneasiness.
不明白我到底是归乡
Not sure I’m going home
还是离乡!
or leaving home!
朋友
My friends,
这是我的鲁凯公主
This is my princess.
长得很漂亮唷
Isn’t she beautiful?
如果你有看到她的时候
If you see her,
告诉她...我已经不再卖命了
please tell her...I've no longer risked my life
我已经回来当一个安分的小警察
and have come back for a peaceful life.
好不好?
Okay?
代表...
Mr. Representative...
最后一瓶 我敬你
It's the last bottle. Cheers!
不用啦 这里还有
No thanks. We still have some here
不然我自己来啦!
Okay, a toast to you!
我这瓶留在这里
I'll leave it here.
慢慢喝 谢谢
Enjoy yourself, thank you.
这个客家人 实在很...
This Hakka is really...
没关系 我去就好 你都还没吃
It's okay, I'll help him. You haven't eaten yet.
时常这样...想摔倒就摔倒
He always...gets drunk and falls down.
来 喝啦...
Come on, cheers...
主席啊
Mr. Representative.
你好 很久不见了
How are you! Long time no see.
好 好啦...
Fine! Fine...
这我老婆啦
This is my wife.
漂亮吗?
Is she pretty?
漂亮...
Yeah...
这瓶拿着 去敬后面那桌
Keep this and propose a toast over there.
你都没去敬后面那桌 快去...
You haven't drunk a toast to them, go ahead...
抱歉...
I’m sorry...
以前在台北当迅雷小组
He was a member of SWAT in Taipei.
你也知道那种队员 只有半条命啊!
You know, they always risk their lives!
有时候早上出门 晚上回不了家
Sometimes they couldn't go back home at night.
他老婆受不了，就这样离家出走
His wife couldn't stand and left him,
心情坏啊!
which put him in bad mood!
有次出勤务 他从三楼掉下来
Once he fell from the 3rd floor when he was on duty.
好想唱歌喔
I wanna sing!
伤到脊椎骨 在医院躺了半年
He hurt his vertebra and stayed in hospital for 6 months.
没办法 出院后调回家乡
After that, he was assigned back to home.
尽量尽量
Try your best.
友子...
Tomoko...
-友子...  -不要碰我!
-Tomoko...  -Don't touch me!
-友子  -叫你不要碰我!
-Tomoko...  -I said don't touch me!
初恋爱情酸甘甜 五种气味唷
First love is sweet, mixed with emotions.
那听一句我爱你 满脸就红吱吱
The word "I love you" makes one flush.
尤其是小姑娘，心内是真欢喜
Especially the girl, she's really happy.
表面上她还假真生气喔
Though she pretends to be angry.
啊...伊...会学巴比补
Oh...yeah...She's pretending.
初恋爱情酸甘甜 五种气味唷
First love is sweet, mixed with emotions.
若听一句我爱你 满面是红吱吱
The word "I love you" makes one flush.
哭夭 看字啦!
Shit! I'm just looking at the characters!
人家你老板娘年纪比你大
Your boss's wife is older than you.
然后又已经有三个小孩
And she has three kids.
最重要的是她老公还没死
What matters is her husband is still alive.
你到底在干嘛呀你?
What the hell are you doing?
你看过青蛙交配没有?
Have you ever seen frogs mating?
一只母青蛙背上贴着两三只公青蛙
A couple of male frogs get on a female's back.
那两三只公青蛙
Those male frogs,
有没有在那边互相吵架的?
do they fight against one another?
没有啊
No! they don't.
那人干嘛去计较那一男一女
Then why should human beings
两男一女的事呢
stick to the monogamy?
你厉害!
You’re hopeless!
阿嘉 出来!
Aga, come out!
给我出来
Come out!
为什么不敢滚出来?
Why don't you come out?
你在跩什么!
Why are you so arrogant?
你每天装那个什么脸啊?
And give me a dirty look every day?
阿嘉!
Aga!
你跩什么...
You smart ass...
你为什么要欺负我
Why did you treat me like that?
我只不过在做我该做的事
I just did what I should do.
你笑什么啦...
What are you laughing at?
你可恶啦你!
Damn you!
喔...被我发现了
Hoo...I got you!
你看
You see,
这是我的鲁凯公主
this is my princess.
长的很漂亮吧
She's pretty, isn't she?
真的很漂亮啦!
She's really pretty!
如果你有看到她的时候 告诉她...
If you see her, please tell her...
你为什么要欺负我
Why did you do this to me?
Why did you treat me like that?
我一个女生
I'm just a girl
离家那么远
away from home
在这里工作
and work here.
又那么辛苦
And I work so hard.
你为什么要欺负我
Why did you treat me like that?
Why did you do this to me?
傍晚 已经进入了日本海
At dusk, we've entered the Sea of Japan.
白天我头痛欲裂
I had a splitting headache in the daytime.
可恨的浓雾
I hate the thick fog,
阻挡了我一整个白天的视线
which blocked my light of sight during the day.
而现在的星光真美
But the stars are beautiful now.
记得你才是中学一年级小女生时
I remember when you were in 7th grade.
就胆敢以天狗食月的农村传说
You dared to challenge my theory of lunar eclipse
来挑战我月蚀的天文理论吗
with the tale of "Sun dog swallow the moon".
再说一件不怕你挑战的理论
There's another theory that can withstand your challenge.
你知道我们现在所看到的星光
Do you know the stars we see now
是自几亿光年远的星球上
are lights reflected from planets
所发射过来的吗
several hundred million light years away?
哇 几亿光年发射出来的光
Wow, light reflected several hundred million years ago.
我们现在才看到
And we haven't seen them until now.
几亿光年的台湾岛和日本岛
In several hundred million years,
又是什么样子呢?
what will Taiwan and Japanese Islands look like?
山还是山 海还是海
Mountains and seas will still be there.
却不见了人
But the people will be gone.
我想再多看几眼星空
I'd like to look at the starry sky a little longer.
在这什么都善变的人世间里
In this changeable world,
我想看一下永恒
I want to see what eternity is.
遇见了要往台湾避冬的乌鱼群
I met a shoal of mullet heading for Taiwan for the winter,
我把对你的相思寄放在其中的一只
and my love was deposited on one of them.
希望你的渔人父亲可以捕获
Hope your fisherman father will catch it.
友子 尽管他的气味辛酸
Tomoko, though it smells bad,
你也一定要尝一口
you should have a bite.
你会明白...
You'll understand...
我不是抛弃你 我是舍不得你
I didn't mean to leave you.
我在众人熟睡的甲板上反覆低喃
I'm moaning on the silent deck late at night
我不是抛弃你 我是舍不得你
that I was reluctant to leave you.
你真的期待我们这些破铜烂铁?
Do you really expect anything form us?
可是我过了十五年
Fifteen years have passed,
还不是一样失败
I am failed as before.
可是我真的不差!
But actually I'm not that bad!
天亮了 但又有何关系
Day breaks, but who cares?
反正日光总是带来浓雾
For the sunlight always brings thick mist.
黎明前的一段恍惚
In a trance before dawn.
我见到了日后的你韶华已逝
I see the aged you in the future
日后的我发秃眼垂
and the aged me with bald head and falling eyes.
晨雾如飘雪 覆盖了我额上的皱纹
Morning mist covers my wrinkles on the forehead, just like snow
骄阳如烈焰 焚枯了你秀发的乌黑
The sun scorches your black hair, just like flame
你我心中最后一点余热完全凋零
Finally, I lose you.
友子...
Tomoko...
请原谅我这身无用的躯体
Please forgive my cowardice.
你...
You...
那些信件非常重要
Those letters are very important.
不管怎么样
Anyway,
你一定要交到那个女孩手里
You should send the letters to that girl.
糟糕...
Oh, jeez...
谁弄的啊
Who did this?
傻傻的你 这会判刑耶!
Idiot, you'll be put into jail.
早叫你退回日本了还偷拆别人邮包
I told you to return the mail back but you unpacked it instead.
恒春郡海角七号
Cape No.7, Hengchun county.
小岛友子?
Kojima Tomoko?
我怎么不记得有这个人?
Why don't I remember this person?
这如果还在 应该也大我没几岁呀!
We are about the same age if she's still alive
海上气温16度
It's 16 ℃ on the sea
风速12节、水深97米
with a 12-knot wind speed and a 97-meter water depth.
已经看见了几只海鸟
A couple of seabirds are flying pass.
预计明天入夜前我们即将登陆
We're landing before tomorrow nightfall.
友子...
Tomoko...
我把我在台湾的相簿都留给你
I left you all my photos taken in Taiwan.
就寄放在你母亲那儿
They were left with your mother.
但我偷了其中一张
But I took one of them with me.
是你在海边玩水的那张
That's the one in which you were playing by the sea.
照片里的海没风也没雨
The sea was calm,
照片里的你，笑得就像在天堂
and you were smiling, as if in paradise.
不管你的未来将属于谁
Whoever your lover will be,
谁都配不上你
he can't be good enough for you.
原本以为我能将美好回忆妥善打包
I'd thought I could pack my beautiful memories up.
到头来却发现我能携走的只有虚无
But I realize that what I take away ends up being nothing.
我真的很想妳!
I really miss you!
啊 彩虹!
Oh, rainbow!
但愿这彩虹的两端
Wish the rainbow arched across the sea
足以跨过海洋 连结我和妳
and connected you and me.
当阳光再次回到那...
When sunshine again comes back to...
飘着雨的国境之南
to the rainy southern country...
我会试着把...
I will try to...
那一年的故事...再接下去说完
finish the story... the story in that year.
当阳光再次...
When sunshine again...
这线那么多条 真的不好弹...
So many strings, it's hard to do it...
这慢歌耶!
Please, it's a slow song!
很简单的东西，又没几个和弦
It's really easy, just a few chords.
拜托!
Come on!
不然 你明天提早来练好不好?
What about... you coming here earlier for practice tomorrow morning?
好啦...
All right...
是说这两条都没用到
I don't need to use these two strings.
不能把它剪掉吗
Can they be cut off?
不行啦 什么剪掉!
No! Cut off?
不行就不行 那么大声干嘛?
All right, why did you shout out?
你有去找那信里的女孩吗
Have you looked for that girl?
我找了...不过还没找到...
Yes...But didn't find her...
我会再找的
I'll try harder
歌词...
The lyrics...
我知道 我会再修啦!
I know, I'll revise them!
那...我先回去修词啰!
Then... see you!
我，关灯
Ah, the light's still on.
我来 我来就好
Okay, I'll turn it off.
好啦...你们自己看他行不行啦!
All right... It's up to you guys!
啊 应该没什么问题吧
Er, He can do it well, I think.
应该可以啦
I think so!
干!
Damn it!
要回答得这么快吗 不考虑就回答
You guys answer without thinking, it's so quick.
我老人家耶!
I'm a senior!
我心肝不是铁打的 我也会伤心耶!
I'm hurt, my heart's broken!
...人是你找来的 又不是我们找的
...It's you who bring him here, not we.
对啊 我们跟他又不熟
Yeah, we don't even know him.
茂伯 我没关系啦!
It's okay, Uncle Mao, never mind me!
别装了啦 饿鬼还装客气
Stop pretending! I know what you want.
会弹贝斯就那么嚣张
You're cocky as you can play bass guitar.
难道就不能有两个弹贝斯的吗
Why can't we have 2 bassists?
我不管 给我弹什么都好啦!
I don't care, I shall play some kind of instrument.
我一定要上台表演啦!
I must perform on the stage!
干 我国宝耶!
Shit! I'm important here!
友子 我已经平安着陆
Tomoko, I've landed safely.
七天的航行
After the seven-day voyage,
我终于踩上我战后残破的土地
I finally step on my ruined hometown after war.
可是我却开始思念海洋
But I begin to miss the sea.
这海洋为何总是站在
Why does the sea always stand at
希望和灭绝的两个极端
the two extremes of hope and despair?
这是我的最后一封信
This is my last letter to you.
待会我就会把信寄出去
I'll mail all of them later.
这容不下爱情的海洋
The sea can't tolerate love,
至少还容得下相思吧!
but at least has room for lovesickness.
友子 我的相思你一定要收到
Tomoko, I hope my lovesickness finds you well.
这样你才会原谅我一点点
Only then will you forgive me a little bit.
我想我会把你放在我心里一辈子
I think I'll keep you in my heart all my life,
就算娶妻、生子
even if I get married and have babies.
在人生重要的转折点上
At some turning points in my life,
一定会浮现...
I'm bound to think of you.
你提着笨重的行李逃家
The girl left home with heavy luggages,
在遣返的人潮中，你孤单地站着
standing alone in the crowd,
你戴着那顶...
and wearing the white hat
存了好久的钱才买来的白色针织帽
which you brought with the money you'd saved for a long time.
是为了让我能在人群中发现你吧!
That's to let me recognize you in the crowd, right?
我看见了...我看见了...
I got you...I got you...
你安静不动地站着
You stood there silently,
- 旧地址  - 海角七号...海角?
- An old address, any body knows?  - Cape No.7...NO.
你像七月的烈日
just like the sun in July.
让我不敢再多看你一眼
So bright that I daren't glance at you any more.
你站得如此安静
I saw you standing there silently.
我刻意冰凉的心 却又顿时燃起
My cold heart was lit up at that moment.
我伤心 又不敢让遗憾流露
I was sad, but had to hide my feelings.
我心里嘀咕 嘴巴却一声不吭
I muttered in my heart without saying anything.
我知道 思念这庸俗的字眼
I know my lovesickness
将如阳光下的黑影
is the shadow under the sunshine.
我逃他追...我追他逃...
It'll chase me when I flee and flee when I chase it...
一辈子
in my whole life.
为什么发愁呢
Why are you so sad?
感情?工作?
Because of love? Or work?
是我们害的吗
Or because of us?
我是想这样下雨明天表演怎么办
I just worry about the show if it rains like that tomorrow.
友子小姐...
Miss Tomoko...
难道你不期待彩虹吗
Don't you expect the rainbow?
友子
Tomoko
我把自己的愧疚写成最后一封信
I wrote my guilt into the last letter
代替我去当面跟你忏悔
to show you my apology.
这样我才会原谅自己一点点
That's how I can forgive myself a little bit.
喂 你们两只马
Hey, you two guys!
明天你们真的这样就甘愿了?
This is what you want for tomorrow's show?
我昨晚想了一整晚没睡
I was sleepless last night, thinking that...
我弹月琴弹五十多年了
For more than fifty years, I've played yu-kin,
明天第一次上台竟然拿这支在摇
but end up shaking this for my first show.
喂 你啊!
Hey, you guy!
你唱歌也很好听啊
You can sing very well!
你唱歌也很好听啊!
明天难道就不想哼两句?
Don't you want to sing tomorrow?
我觉得喔...
I think...
你安静 我没问你!
Shut up. I didn't ask you !
喂 那个灌篮高手
Hey, slam dunker.
红色不流行了啦
Red is not popular now.
阿嘉说他先在家里修改歌词
Aga said that he wanted to revise lyrics at home.
他叫我们先自己练习
He asked us to practice first.
我今天在机场买东西要送给你们
I bought some presents for you at airport.
大大 这是祖灵的眼睛
Dada, this is Ancestors' Eyes.
保护你的身体健康成长
To protect your health.
谢谢
Thank you.
马拉桑!
Malasun!
这是蝶蛹之珠
This is Marutjamulang.
希望你的勤劳带给你
I wish your diligence will bring you
很大很大的财富
a lot of fortune.
谢谢...我需要财富...
Thank you... I need fortune.
水蛙!
Frog!
这是手脚之珠
This is Magazaigaw.
让你的手艺更好
Let you have better craftsmanship
劳马
Rauma
这是孔雀之珠
This is Za-aw.
守护你对你太太坚定的爱情
It can guard your firm love for your wife.
这是泪痕之珠
This is Lozegnagadaw.
这个 对我妻子最不舍的思念
This is my greatest longest for my wife.
戴着吧 都买了
But I've bought it, take it anyway.
有爱情 才会有思念呀!
You miss her because of love.
谢谢...
Thank you...
茂伯呀!
Uncle Mao!
鸭尾他阿公现在只是铃鼓手而已喔
Ya Wei's grandfather is just a tambourine player.
什么铃鼓手 铃鼓手又怎样?
So what? Playing tambourine is also important.
茂伯呀!这是日光之珠
Uncle Mao, this is Mulimulidan.
象征你尊贵的地位!
It represents your honorable position.
我这有妈祖耶 不会吵架吗?
I've got MaZu. Won't they fight?
不会啦!
No. No. They won't.
大家都是一家人 怎么会吵架
We're family. Why should we fight?
讲到一家人
Speaking of family,
其实 我有准备一个东西
Actually, I've prepared something.
就我们是一个乐团对不对
We're a band. Right?
要让人家看起来真的很有整体感
We need to be unified.
所以之前我有去订作一个东西
So I had customized something earlier.
反正今天我觉得最适合
Today it is the right time to give it to you.
我特别订做了一件这个...
I've specially customized a piece of...
其实是我们的制服
actually, It is our uniform.
表演的时候可以穿的
We can wear it on the show.
制服?
Uniform?
马拉桑
Malasun,
千年传统 全新感受
Thousand years of history, completely new feelings.
一家人的制服
Family's uniform.
不好意思 借坐一下
Sorry to bother you, We want to sit your place.
你们在这里忙 我先去休息
You keep working. I'd like to go sleep.
微风告知春天来访
The breeze informs of spring's coming.
纷纷绽放的花朵香气里
The fragrance of blossoming flowers
令人想起远方的妳
reminds me of you far away.
如春日阳光守护下绽放的花朵
You're like blossoming flowers, guarded by spring sunshine.
未来希望之光也会照耀我们吧
The light of hope will guide us in the future.
我们各自踏上各自抉择的道路
We set foot on separated roads we choose.
我终于知道为什么大家都说
Now I know why everyone said that
我以前唱歌太用力
I sang too hard before.
阿嘉 我...
Aga, I...
你们人到齐了吗?换你们彩排了
Are you all here? It is your turn.
可以了吗?
Is it OK?
孝介 可以了吗?
Akari, is it OK?
-ok!
-是的 我知道了
ok!
Yeah. I see.
麻烦妳了
Please
跟妳商量一下好不好
Can you do me a favor?
等一下我去烧一张光碟
I'll make a DVD later.
把我们的商标打在那个大荧幕上面
Then put my logo on the big screen.
人这么多 效果一定...
There're so many people, it must be....
你不要太过分...
Don't be so greedy.
已经给你这样子了
You've got your uniforms.
辛苦了!
Thanks a lot !
Thanks a lot!
我们先到饭店里面休息一下
We can go to hotel to have a rest.
友子 可以先请厨房先准备餐点吗?
Tomoko, could you please ask them to prepare the meal?
那警察是暖场乐团的吉他手!
The policeman is guitarist in the warming-up band.
警察?
Policeman?
没想到你在台湾这么受欢迎
I don't know that you are so popular in Taiwan.
友子小姐
Miss Tomoko
彩虹!
Rainbow
可以给我一根烟吗?
Could you give me a cigarette?
别跟我说你听不懂日文
Don't tell me you cant'tspeak Japanese.
今天过后
After today
你就不必看到我们这些讨厌的人了
you don't need to see us anymore.
我爱上阿嘉了!
I fall in love with Aga.
我不是没谈过恋爱
I've fallen in love before,
只是这次最奇怪
but this time is so strange.
不知道到底算不算?
I don't know if it is love or not?
日本人哪懂爱情?
Japanese don't understand what is love.
你被日本人伤过心吗?
Have you been hurt by Japanese?
怎么对我们那么偏见?
Why are you so prejudiced to us?
是大大的父亲吗?
It is Dada's father?
你一定被男人伤得很重
You must be hurt by him badly.
早就心死了
My heart died long ago.
我也在寻找一位心死的恒春女孩
I'm looking for a girl in HengChun. Her heart died too.
不过他现在大概也八十岁了吧
But she may be 80 years old now.
他也和我一样叫友子
She is called Tomoko too.
我在阿嘉那边看到一个邮包
I saw a package at Aga's.
一个找不到地址的日本邮包
A Japanese package with an unknown address.
更正确的说
More precisely
应该是七封情书
It's seven love letters.
日本老先生死了之后
After Japanese old man died,
他女儿在他柜子里找到
His daughter found them in his cabinet
替他寄过来的
and mailed them for her father.
可惜60年前的旧地址已经没人记得
It's a pity that nobody remembers the old address 60 years ago.
我...偷看过那些情书
I...had secretly read those love letters.
那是我所见过最真最美的思念
It's the most beautiful and sincere love I have seen.
一定可以医治一位心死的老人!
I'm sure that it can cure the broken heart of the old lady.
你怎么了?
What's the matter with you?
把邮包送到这个地址
Send the package to this address.
那个也叫友子的女孩住在这里
The girl called Tomoko lives there
...你怎么知道?
...How do you know?
她是我祖母!
She is my grandmother!
那...我把邮包拿给你啊!
Then...I can give the package to you.
我对她做了很不好的事
I did something bad to her.
她已经不理我了.
She doesn't want to see me anymore.
快去吧!
Go now!
快去啊!
阿嘉...
Aga...
找到邮包的主人了!
I found the owner of the package.
你可以现在去吗?
Can you go now?
有这么急吗?
Is it so urgent?
阿嘉...
Aga...
今天晚上表演结束
After tonight's concert
我就要和日本唱片公司的人
I'll go back to Japan
一起回日本
with the Japanese album company's staff.
他们邀请我到日本唱片公司当公关
They invited me to work in Japanese album company.
你答应了?
Did you say yes to them?
记得告诉我
Please remember to tell me
那个也叫友子的女孩的长相喔!
What the girl called Tomoko looks like.
这是勇士之珠
This is Vuliauvuliau.
他会保护你的荣誉和勇敢
It will guard your honor and bravery.
我会假装你忘了我
I'll pretend that you have forgotten me.
假装你将你我的过往
pretend that you have removed our common memories
像候鸟一般从记忆中迁徙
like a migrant bird.
假装你已走过寒冬迎接春天
pretend that you have move forward.
我会假装...
I'll pretend ...
一直到自以为一切都是真的!
until I believe everything I've imaged is real.
然后...
Then,
祝你一生永远幸福!
I wish you happy life.
有人在吗?
Is anybody there?
你到底跟阿嘉说什么啊?
What did you say to Aga?
靠海边的朋友
Those audiences near to sea.
麻烦你们站进来一点
Please come closer.
现在在退潮
The tide is ebbing now.
麻烦你们往里面靠一点
Please come closer.
这边的朋友，麻烦你们靠进来一点
谢谢!
Thank you!
小心!靠进来一点
Be careful! Come closer.
你有没有搞错啊?
What's wrong with you?
到底什么时候了 你还叫他去送信?
Why did you ask him to deliver package at this moment.
妳到底有没有进入状况啊?
What's wrong with you?
经理
Mr. Manager
要不要跟代表会主席联络一下?
Should I call Mr.Representative?
他可能在人群里面.
He may be in the crowd.
找他有个屁用啊?
What good will it do?
妳赶快给我想办法 听到没有?
You must find a solution. Do you hear me?
友子小姐
Miss Tomoko
他们有谁可以唱的吗?
Is there anyone who can sing?
我很能唱!
I can sing very well!
不信的话 妳可以问他
You can ask him if you don't trust me.
妳问他啊!
Ask him!
啊 阿嘉回来了!
Ah. Aga is back!
快...快上台...
Hurry up. Get on the stage now.
你怎么去那么久?
What took you so long?
他们两个不是仇人吗?
Don't they hate each other?
留下来...
Please stay...
或者我跟妳走!
or I will go with you!
不要紧张 放轻松
Don't be nervous. Relax.
谁紧张?神经病!
Who is nervous? Psycho!
十...
Ten!
九...
Nine!
八...
Eight!
七...
Seven!
六...
Six!
五...
Five!
四...
Four!
三!
Three!
二...
Two!
一...
One!
想搜集夏天的热
I wanna collect the warmth of summer.
穿越叫幸福的河
Cross the river called Happiness
想做吞大象的蛇
Wanna be a snake swallowing elephant.
不自量力说真的 有何不可?
It sounds so stupid, but why not?
我想写歌
I wanna write a song.
当天是空的 地是干的
When the sky is empty, and the earth is dry.
我要为妳倒进狂热
I'll pour passion for you.
让妳疯狂 让妳渴
Make you crazy, and make you thirsty.
让全世界知道妳是我的
Let the whole world know that you are mine
天气疯了 海水滚了
The weather has gone mad, and the sea has been boiled.
所以我要无乐不作
So I want to do everything about happiness.
不要浪费每一刻 快乐
Don't waste every happy moment.
当梦的天行者
Fly your dream bravely
像妳这样的天使
An angel like you
该有翅膀和名字
Should have wings and name
该美丽中带着刺
Should be beautiful with thorns.
该很认真的属于我一次
Should belong to me for once.
当天是空的 地是干的
When the sky is empty, and the earth is dry.
我要为妳倒进狂热
I'll pour passion for you.
让妳疯狂 让妳渴
Make you crazy, and make you thirsty.
让全世界知道妳是我的
Let the whole world know that you are mine.
天气疯了 海水滚了
The weather has gone mad, and the sea has been boiled.
所以我要无乐不作－阿公...
So I want to do everything about happiness.
-Grandpa...
不要浪费每一刻 快乐
Don't waste every happy moment.
当梦的天行者
Fly you dream bravely.
当天是空的 地是干的
When the sky is empty, and the earth is dry.
我要为妳倒进狂热
I'll pour passion for you.
让妳疯狂 让妳渴
Make you crazy, and make you thirsty.
让全世界知道妳是我的
Let the whole world know that you are mine.
世界末日就尽管来吧
Although the end of world will come.
我会继续无乐不作
I still continue to do everything about happiness.
不会浪费爱妳的 快乐
I won't waste my happiness of loving you.
当梦的天行者
Fly your dream bravely.
要快乐 喔～
Be happy, oh~
不要紧张嘛!怕什么?
Don't be nervous! What are you afraid of?
这支给你摇
You shake this one.
如果海会说话 如果风爱上砂
If sea can speak. If wind falls in love with sands.
如果有些想念遗忘在某个长假
If my long was forgotten in a long vacation.
任记忆里的爱情在时间潮汐里喧哗
Let my love in the memory grows with time.
非得等春天远了 夏天才近了
The summer won't come until the spring is gone.
我是在回首时终于懂得
When I look back, I finally realize that
当阳光再次回到那
When sunshine comes back to
飘着雨的国境之南
the rainy southern country again.
我会试着把...
I'll try to...
那一年的故事
finish the story
再接下去说完
in that year.
当阳光再次离开那
When the sunshine leaves
太睛朗的国境之南
the too sunny Southern country again.
妳会不会把...
Will you return all the love...
妳曾带走的爱
you have taken away
在告别前用微笑全归还
With smile before you leave.
海很蓝 星光灿烂
The sea is very blue, the shine of stars is so bright.
我仍空着我的臂弯
My arms still hold nothing.
天很宽 在我独自唱歌的夜晚
The sky is so wide when I sing alone at night.
请原谅我的爱
Please forgive me for
诉说的太缓慢
telling my love so late.
这是孔雀之珠
This is Za-aw.
她守护着你坚贞不移的爱情!
It will guard your firm love.
当阳光再次回到那
When sunshine comes back to
飘着雨的国境之南
the rainy southern country again.
我会试着把...
I'll try to...
那一年的故事
finish the story
再接下去说完
the story in that year.
彩虹的事 谢谢你!
About the rainbow, thank you!
没事...
You are welcome.
妳会不会把...
Will you return all the love
妳曾带走的爱
you've taken away
在告别前用微笑全归还
With smile before you leave.
没关系的 就让他们再唱一首吧
Never mind. Let them sing one more.
不行啊 他们只准备两首歌
No, they only have two songs.
过来啦!
Come on!
茂伯!
Uncle Mao!
劳马...
Rauma...
男孩看见野玫瑰
The boy sees a wild rose.
啊 这首歌我也会唱
Ah. I know the song too.
清早盛开真鲜美
It is so beautiful to blossom in the morning.
急忙跑去近前看
He rushes to see it.
说看越觉欢心
It makes him so happy.
玫瑰玫瑰红玫瑰
Rose, Rose, the Red rose.
荒地上的玫瑰
The rose in the wildness.
友子小姐
Miss Tomoko
我是这信件中老师的女儿
I am the daughter of teacher in those letters.
这木盒是在父亲房间衣柜里发现的
I found this wooden box in my father's bedroom cabinet.
我的父亲已经在今年一月病逝了
My father had passed away in January this year.
我仔细的看过里面的每一封信
I read every letter carefully.
很难想像木盒里的秘密...
The secret hidden in wooden box
是如此的美丽而辛酸
is so beautiful and heart-broken.
现在我就代替我的父亲
On behalf of my father, I send
把这些六十年前的信
all letters written 60 years ago
全部寄过去给你
to you now.